this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
or / software this is Robert bloomin for
software engineering radio I have with
me today dr. Anil
Madhav a petty dr. Madhav a petty earned
his doctoral degree at the University of
Cambridge computer laboratory in the
systems Research Group he is a senior
research fellow at Cambridge where he
was on the team that developed the Xen
hypervisor leads the Oh camel labs group
and is developing the Mirage cloud
operating system he is also the
co-author of the recently published book
real-world Oh camel functional
programming for the masses Anil welcome
to software engineering radio I think
you're over it good to be here
today we'll be talking about the Mirage
microkernel please tell the listeners
anything more about your background
you'd like them to know I think my my
discovery of functional programming is
is fairly typical of a lot of people
that define themselves using these
techniques more and more so I started
working on open source in the late 90s
and a lot of my initial code was
actually developing online games things
like muds and multi period multi-user
games are developed in in C and C++ and
I found myself working a lot in PHP
because that was a very convenient way
in the late 90s to build websites and it
worked in open source software like
horde and M which is very popular web
mail system and I found myself working
on an operating system called open BSD
increasingly and what open BSD had was
the UNIX philosophy but it had a real
emphasis on correctness and stability
and simplicity and I found myself
working on little bits of infrastructure
like OpenSSH and a lot of the other
demons that form
can be used either used by other
operating systems as well and really
enjoying this emphasis on a nice clean
UNIX philosophy when I started my PhD I
actually ended up trying to do a lot of
work in open BSD to make it more secure
so I worked on bounce checkers for the
the compiler to check for common errors
and after a while I just got exhausted
because it was so very very difficult
trying to build stable reliable systems
on top of a foundation was an unsafe
language like C and during my PhD I
discovered programming on camel which
I'll talk about more in this interview
and for the last at 12 or 13 years I've
almost exclusively been building systems
typically for data centers and other
distributed systems using a camel and
some of the really nice properties that
a camel brings to the table are that
it's very much like C so you don't have
to be a magic mathematician or a
highly-trained computer scientist to
understand it it's very very accessible
to people who are familiar with working
in low-level systems so I just want to
emphasize that my background isn't
really a very very deep mathematical
training it's just a normal programmer
trying to build systems that work simply
and as efficiently as possible your
biographical background is giving us
some insight into how you evolved from
the BSD model to the microkernel model
I'd like to come back to that but first
can you explain the difference between a
microkernel and a monolithic kernel I
certainly can so whenever you have a
general purpose operating system it it
tries to provide you as as convenient an
environment as possible for serving up
application needs so if you take a Linux
kernel it not only provides you with the
ability to boot on a lot of hardware it
provides you with device drivers to
drive the physical Hardware using a nice
well-defined API
well mostly nice sometimes and sometimes
well-defined
like the sockets API but it also
provides you in addition to these device
drivers a lot of other resources for
example it provides you with a tcp/ip
stack that can let you do network
communication using well-defined
protocols it provides you with a shell
interface where you can actually execute
scripts and other code it provides you
with many many storage protocols and
systems that will that will decide
exactly what the layout of your disk
looks like and all of these together
form a very clustered environment in
which you have to obey what the colonel
wants you to do in order to make any
progress a microkernel has a slightly
different emphasis a microkernel there's
many many different services that
operate independently that minimize the
amount of privilege they have and they
have to inter communicate with other
components in the system to give you a
reliable service
so a microkernel is much more like a
distributed system where if I wanted to
have a network stack communicate with my
disk in a microkernel I would have two
separate processes running that would
that I would have to make talk to each
other in order to serve up a file from
the disk over the network so micro
kernels are from our computer science
perspective a much more elegant way to
build systems but where they fall over
is usually a from a performance
perspective so Linux by being a
monolithic kernel or or even FreeBSD or
open BSD have the advantage that by
running everything in in a single
address space in the kernel they can
gain efficiencies of scale so they can
contact switch between a network stack
and a storage stack and also their
memory subsystem all within the same
process space and because we do this a
lot typically when when building network
systems they're just faster and more
efficient than a typical microkernel but
then in the late 90s a bunch of people
from MIT and also in Cambridge in my
group started looking for hybrids
between micro kernels and monolithic
kernels and these are called XO kernels
and how these work is that they let the
entire application link to kernel
subsystems and specialize themselves
based on what their application needs
are so for example if I'm running a web
server I might not want to share my
tcp/ip stack or my network card with any
other drivers I only want my operating
system to serve web traffic so in this
case there's no point
protecting the physical device driver
from the application and what an XO
kernel lets you do is to directly link
these systems together and form a
specialized kernel that will only serve
web traffic and it's very hard to
multiplex this with other users or any
other applications because it is
designed for one thing and one thing
only
and so XO kernels never really took off
because but the
they were in the late 90s the
performance kings of operating systems
and so it's in this background that we
came to looking in Mirage which is that
you have micro kernels which are the
elegant kings of operating system design
but rarely used in real desktop and
service systems they're they're quite
common in mobile and embedded but but
less so in in the in the in the bigger
operating systems and then you have
exokernel which is these these nice
hybrids and then you have monolithic
kernels which form the basis for most of
the operating systems that the listeners
will be familiar with so could you give
us a picture of a if I'm in a data
center have a box what do I put on the
box is it a hypervisor do I have
multiple of these or one per box how
what's the architecture for from the
hardware up of a machine that's running
these kernels got it so now if you if
you look at the data center from the
early 2000s say before VMware came in
the same you would have to install a
physical operating system typically
Windows or Linux on a on a on a server
machine and you would have to configure
that exactly the specification that you
want so typically you would install a
database install a web server install a
directory service of some kind and you'd
have to make sure that each of these
services aren't cross talking to each
other and that the the backup solutions
and so on are all in place for these
machines so the revolution that came
about with with VMware and Xen which are
2 2 hypervisors is that they had the
ability to carve up a physical machine
into multiple virtual machines
so taking Xen is an example because
that's what I'm most familiar with you
first of all install Xen on a physical
machine and when Xen boots up it's an
extremely simple hypervisor it's called
a type 1 hypervisor that only does three
things it it looks at all the memory
president of the machine and it looks at
the number of CPUs and cores and it it
categorizes those and it figures at the
interrupt system so this is the system
that external device is used to
communicate with the rest of the machine
it then knows nothing about how to run
these physical devices so what it does
is that it spins up a special guest
operating system so typically this
all domain 0 and this domain 0 is Linux
usually or it can be solaris or net bsd
and hopefully soon freebsd and this
domain 0 takes care of running the
physical device drivers now this
wouldn't be very interesting if you can
only run a domain 0 so then also lets
you spin up multiple domain use which
are guest operating systems and these
have the illusion that they're running
inside a physical machine but in fact
what's happening behind the scenes is a
Xen is faking out their physical device
drivers and proxying any requests that
you have for the network of the block
devices to the real physical devices
present in dom 0 so the stack as the
operating system sees it is that the Xen
hypervisor boots up in the very
beginning and it boots up a domain 0
which is the the physical domain that
runs all the physical device drivers and
then you have many many domains which
form the guests so in a typical Xen
installation you have a few hundred
virtual machines that all think they're
running in the physical instance but in
fact communicate through the domain 0 to
to actually run their their their own
networking needs and so the revolution
came about in manageability because I
could take a bunch of physical machines
that were formerly running Windows or
Linux but perhaps weren't utilized at
100% so typically if you're running a
database on alloted or a website it
might be running ten percent of the time
and we could consolidate all of these
virtual machines into a single Xen box
that was then fully utilized and these
could be managed through nice software
interfaces so the stack itself is so
it's about three or four levels deep now
yeah you have the Xen hypervisor you
have domain 0 running which is the the
physical domain you have the guest
virtual machines running which run their
own kernels and then finally have of
course the user spaces in those kernels
which actually excuse the application at
hand and now are you talking about the
generic virtualization architecture or
is is it the same when you're running
mirage kernels as the guest VMs so so
this is where mirage comes in so one of
the frustrations with this software
stack is that it was amazing for
consolidating physical machines if I
have a hundred Windows machines and I do
not want to touch them because I'm not
entirely sure what's running on them
then I can just consolidate the musings
without having to change any of my
operating procedures in the long-term
though this leads us to this salad model
where we keep building up these layers
of abstraction in our software stacks so
every 10 years we tend to add a new
layer because we're not quite sure what
to do with the old ones so if you look
at a modern application server you have
the hypervisor you have the operating
system kernel you have user space then
increasingly in the last ten years we
use high-level languages so we have
language runtime that has some garbage
collector like a JVM or the.net runtime
then on top of that you have threads and
then on top of that you have application
specific logic so you can see how this
stack is just getting increasingly
complex so what we want to do with
Mirage and this is the reason why it's
called Mirage is that we wanted to push
a lot of this complexity into the
compiler so instead of depending on a
runtime to figure out exactly what all
these layers do we wanted to just say
well why can't I compile a specialized
appliance there for one purpose only and
this should be this is reminiscent of
exokernel and then this the specialized
appliance will have all of the
functionality that it doesn't need
discarded at compile time so the final
thing that I deployed the cloud is a
very very small specialized image and we
can do this for two reasons the first
one is that we no longer have to have
these general-purpose widths Army knife
operating systems because when I run
something in the cloud I can just say I
want to run a web server and a database
and I can spin up a virtual machine for
each one I can pay for them individually
and if I need more database nodes I can
just spin up more nodes if I need more
web server nodes I spin up more nodes
and at no point do I need to shoehorn in
some database functionality into a web
server or a storage server does not have
to become a web server I can just make a
software API call to Amazon or Rackspace
and get a new virtual machine for that
purpose so this has really changed the
way that we have to think about
deploying and managing systems in a in a
DevOps context and Miraj is really
designed to fit into that new world and
really not try to worry too much about
backwards compatibility and the other
thing that has changed from the late 90s
to now is that we don't really care so
much about binary compatibility so it
might have been in the old days that I
had to run word or had to run I
server or had to run my sequel these
days most of the interconnects in the
cloud are done through pretty well
standardized protocols so really what I
want my virtual machine to do is to talk
HTTP to another service or to talk to my
sequel or the the PostgreSQL binary
protocol or to talk some XML RPC or JSON
protocol instead so this means that
within the virtual machine there is no
need for compatibility with Linux or
Windows it's only the external protocols
that we we communicate with that we have
to remain compatible with so Mirage was
formed in a context where we can use the
cloud to give us a nice virtual
framework where we can just build and
build a new operating system but it only
has to support virtual device drivers so
we don't have to support every physical
device in the world and we don't have to
worry so much about backwards
compatibility and we can rethink the
rest of the operating system stack and
the goal with Mirage is to make it as
invisible as possible so I should be
able to write some nice high-level code
and synthesize these nice little
specialized kernels but myself not have
to be a kernel programmer I just want to
write high-level code in or camel in
this case and I have the results
magically optimized way by my compiler
so in many ways it's analogous to what
it must have felt like to write programs
and the early days of computing when you
would just put in some punch cards into
into into a machine and it would
magically you know assemble those and
execute those in a much more efficient
form than you had before through the
years since our compilers tend to just
stop at arbitrary points so when I run
GCC it just stops at the object file
when I run an executable it runs within
a kernel and then it doesn't do any
further optimizations but mirages we
just wanted to look at the entire system
were deploying and try to do
higher-level reasoning and compilation
on top of all of the layers that we have
access to so try to recapture some of
the simplicity that we add in in in in
older computer systems so Neil you've
given us some examples database and web
server give a few other examples briefly
of the type of services that a mirage
kernel would offer so imagine you can
compile anything that you you want to
run the cloud right now you can compile
a mirage equivalent for that so the most
popular one that we're doing so far is
it's compiling up our home pages so of
course
having built mirages we wanted to just
use it for our own personal
infrastructure and so we built a little
blogging in wiki infrastructure and we
turned the mirage website which is on
open module org into a self hosted
entity and we did this in the very early
days of the project the project is been
going forward for years and in the first
year we we got the entire thing self
hosting all the way from the the website
and the DNS infrastructure and what this
brought was although this was in the
early days a very very kind of quickly
hacked a prototype that we published in
I think in music's hot cloud it made it
clear exactly what the type of things we
needed to host an end-to-end service on
the internet were for example let's say
I want to host open mirage at org online
the first thing I need is I need
somewhere to run the DNS this is the
domain name service that resolves open
Mirage or org into a concrete IP address
and so the first thing we did was to
build a DNS server that was the
equivalent of bind or NSD for those
familiar with DNS in Mirage and we
evaluated it against the existing
versions we made it nice and fast and
very sign gave us some funding to
improve the DNS infrastructure therein
in 2010 and we put this live and it was
remarkable how small it was
so this DNS server was 100 kilobytes in
size so compare that to and entires for
example Ubuntu distribution running in
the cloud which is regularly going up to
a gigabytes in size
we had a microkernel that would serve
just DNS in 100 kilobytes of of memory
and so we call these specialized micro
kernels unique kernels there were single
purpose to one thing and if you wanted
to reconfigure them they would they
would just have be recompiled and the
old one destroyed and the new one
deployed so when we had DNS we then
moved on to http because I've served the
traffic and I now want to respond to web
requests but before we can serve HTTP it
turns out well you need to have a TCP
stack and normally Linux gives you a TCP
stack in order to communicate over that
protocol but we didn't have that but
when it comes to building a TCP stack
you also need to have DHCP because you
need to obtain an IP address for Amazon
you need to have an Ethernet stack to
deal with the lower level virtual
Ethernet abstraction and you need to
have device drivers
to actually drive the Zen device driver
so we spent about a year building all of
these in pure camel from scratch and it
became obvious exactly what set of
protocols you needed to run a dedicated
homepage so once we had Ethernet we had
DHCP we had IP we had TCP we have then
wrote an HTTP stack and finally we got
to serve our DNS responses and our HTTP
responses from the home page and this is
very motivational because it means that
we were now convinced that there is
nothing we couldn't do in the Internet
Protocol space to serve up simple
web-based infrastructure and once you
have a web server there's a lot of
things you can do so obviously you can
serve up JavaScript and you can build
restful api s so our home pages have
little examples of tiny rest based
protocols that you can use to update
comments and and so on and so forth
and this is a nice way to to drive one
particular set of functionality but then
once you have all these networking
protocols it became obvious that we also
needed some story for storage and so
this is something we've been developing
the last year is a database based on the
principles of git so instead of having a
conventional file system like fat or
NTFS or ext we decided that we would
actually version control everything so
we wanted to live in a world where every
single unit kernel that was serving our
home pages would actually just form a
node in in a gift version control tree
and so we've been building the
infrastructure such that whenever a
unique kernel starts its pork's its
storage from a git database all of his
changes are written into a branch and
then reconciled and pushed back to a
central git repository which can itself
be hosted in github and because these
these repositories are so small it turns
out that we can actually track the
source code for our unit kernels within
get itself so instead of having a
separate image tracking system that
would track all of the Ubuntu gold
images or the freebsd gold images that
we need well we just compiled a unique
kernel we commit the result which is
typically a megabyte in size into a git
repository and we track the whole thing
as one entire universe of version
control so once we build DNS servers and
we had our home pages running there
we've now got version control running in
storage as well and so this is a good
example of how sometimes you have to
obey existing protocols for example we
have to obey DHCP and tcp/ip but other
times you don't have to listen to
conventional wisdom so in this case we
looked at existing systems Dave Scott
from Citrix built a fat32 equivalent so
we could we could read USB sticks and so
on but we just didn't want to go down
the path of aping existing file systems
because they're very very complicated
there's they're very ill specified and
it's not at all clear that replicating
their functionality would would win us
anything in a unique kernel world so
we're discovering that sometimes just
changing these interfaces and trying
something new is actually a very big win
so get version control system is the big
thing we're working on now in terms of
other uses in the cloud there's actually
the software that runs a cloud itself
and this is actually the thing that
funded and was the reason for building
mirage in the first place
so consider Xen which is running a large
data center and this data center is
perhaps serving a hundred thousand hosts
and these hundred thousand physical
hosts could themselves run a couple of
hundred VMs each so before you know it
you have a data center running this one
bit of software that is running tens of
millions of virtual machines and clearly
you need to have a management stack that
will deal with the concerns of how to
start and stop these VMs in a very very
secure way and just running the virtual
machines itself is not enough you also
need to configure the storage in the
network you also need to configure the
network topology and there's a big life
cycle of things around the datacenter
that you need to control through
software so when Xen started all of this
ran inside a single monolithic domain
called domain 0 and domain 0 is a full
Linux instance and it can not only run
the physical device drivers but it also
runs this management stack so what we
wanted was as Xen grew in importance you
know because if anyone can compromise
this domain you've compromised your
entire system we wanted to fall back to
more of a microkernel world where this
domain 0 could be broken up into lots
and lots of small pieces so a lot of the
upstream Zen developers added support
Andy Warfield's team in UBC for example
added support for breaking up this big
domain zero into lots of small so-called
driver domains and each of these driver
domains would be responsible for just
one tiny part of
running the physical system so for
example my storage stack to my QLogic
HBA could be running a storage domain
that would be driving it and my network
card to my my 10 gigabit network devices
would be running in a different domain
entirely so if my storage device driver
were to crash for some reason then it
would reboot and the networking would be
unaffected so this gives us the ability
to really control this a lot of the
infrastructure in a single host in a
very fine-grained way and therefore
increased reliability and so what Mirage
was really useful for was to build a
control stack for this committee to read
system because of course there's no
point building a microkernel based
system if the thing controlling it is
itself a monolithic kernel I can just
fail at any point so the first fuselage
was actually to just control those n
boxes itself and we've had a huge number
of code contributions from Citrix so who
maintains n so Dave Scott is the the
principle architect behind that john
Ludlum Rob who's Thomas L so a lot of
people have been contributing code for
the express purpose of making Mirage a
good platform to to actually manage them
with itself and this is an ongoing
process so a lot of the pieces of Mirage
have already been integrated into the
design management stack but and we
continue to do so as well so we've we've
gone from lots of self-hosting which
drives one particular cloud use case and
also building very low-level Cystic
components for Xen that we need very
fine gain control over and we can use
the same sets of source code to serve
both of those as well so this obviously
lets us as a small team can I build up
some very complicated components from
very well-structured modular pieces
written in written in a kettle erased a
number of interesting points in that
description I wanted to follow up on the
resource consumption issue how much work
can you get out of the same box running
micro kernels versus running monolithic
Linux kernels running multiple services
how does it do on a resource consumption
standpoint in delivering throughput at
lower cost that's it that's a it's a
good question it the answer really
depends on the nature of your workloads
so if you are running in a mobile phone
system for example where you need some
very strong isolation between certain
components for example your 3g firmware
might need to be completely far walled
away from your App Store and Android so
at this point you you care less about
resource consumption and more about
strong isolation when you move to more
cloud like workloads what these
typically looked like is you're just
serving up a lot of network connections
and you want to do this with the minimum
resource usage so in this world a
traditional microkernel would actually
be very slow because in order to serve a
single network connection it would need
to contact switch across many many
different domains
now a virtualized monolithic kernel for
example Linux running on top of Zen
running running on Amazon would also
actually be quite slow because every
time it transmits a packet from an
application the application would
synthesize the response it would then go
from its user space into the virtual
kernel which would then go from the
virtual kernel into the domain 0 kernel
in Zen which would then go to a go to
the outside world in a Mirage world we
we collapse a lot of the stacks in the
in in the in the virtual address space
so this means that for Mirage appliance
to reply back to a web response it only
has to go from domain 0 to the virtual
unit kernel and it would just be
responded to immediately so there's no
kind of bouncing within of layers within
the virtual appliance itself so we've
we've actually done some some
benchmarking of this and there's two
major wins the first one is just in
straightforward throughput you can build
systems that that work at ten gigabit
speeds for example and they require
significant less CPU than you do in in
in other systems and the other is really
not obvious when is actually in latency
because you have to go through fewer
layers of abstraction you actually
respond with very very low latency to to
external application requests and the
other thing is boot time so because
these unique hurdles are so simple you
can put them in milliseconds so in other
words if I I want to absolutely reduce
the amount of money I'm spending on the
cloud I could respond to an incoming
network connection by spinning up a
unique kernel that would boot up and say
ten milliseconds and
then as soon as it's done they would
just shut itself down again so instead
of time to take a heavyweight approach
by spinning up a big Linux virtual
machine I could just spin up tiny tiny
DeLuna kernels on demand and have an
extremely elastic approach to to scaling
my resources so a good fellow for this
is a paper we published in the
architectural support for programming
languages and operating systems in 2013
so if you go to the Mirage homepage we
have a paper called unique kernels
library operating system to the cloud
and we have a number of benchmarks in
there which demonstrate dns and tcp and
web were loads an open flow using Mirage
versus equivalents in a normal software
stack such as Linux we'll link to that
paper in the show notes now if I've
understood this correctly you might have
Mirage running a web server Mirage
running database they need to
communicate so you've pushed the
communication overhead into the Zen
layer is that correct well so this is
where things started getting a bit
complicated if you're running a database
and a web server in a normal Linux stack
then if they're running in the same
machine you might configure for example
my sequel to use a UNIX domain socket on
the same host to connect to the web
server now if these are running in a
virtual machine on the cloud you
typically are forced to use tcp/ip and
so this means that no matter where these
virtual machines are running they will
always have to communicate by
marshalling a tcp/ip connection and
connecting to the other side and hope
for the best
now this is this is very efficient but
it's also not as efficient as it could
be because you the best way to get
faster is by doing this work so Zen
supports a number of highly efficient
shared memory abstractions that if
you're on the same host between the same
virtual machine you can directly connect
via a shared memory ring and have
extremely fast so we're talking about 60
to 100 gigabits of throughput just by
going over the shared memory rings but
the problem is how do you manage these
rings because if if if I know that my
web server is on the same physical host
as my database then I can I can
negotiate these connections but if I
live relocate this virtual machine to it
and host and the the connection will
break because obviously there's no
shared memory connection anymore and on
the cloud one of the really nice
features is that you can just move
virtual machines or run physical hosts
without them knowing about it so this is
one good example of where Linux or
FreeBSD is approached networking just
breaks down because if I had a single
connection it's actually very very
difficult to without the application
knowing redirect the connection to a
shared memory channel or and then switch
TCP whenever a live migration happens so
in Mirage we're developing a new
networking stack called Fable and the
idea is that this is this is a network
stack that we'll understand based on
probing its environment if it can make a
shared memory connection and if it can't
it will fall back to a normal tcp/ip
connection and if if that breaks it will
try to find other strategies to connect
so the idea is that in the cloud
environment we just really don't know
anything about our environment and so a
networking stack has to figure out more
details about hydrants on so I gave a
talk at FOSDEM about this which is the
one of the biggest European open source
meetings and I had a quiz asking people
about there any myths about Io and it
turns out that almost no one in the
audience had a complete understanding of
how all of the different things that
form a modern networking stack fit
together because we have so many layers
now that stuff is just insanely
complicated and then when you add on
security for example SSL or things of
that nature it gets even more
complicated because you have to not only
manage network connections but also
security keys and so on so one of the
most interesting projects going on right
now in Mirage is a clean slate SSL stack
that tries to abstract away a lot of the
complexity but keep secure key material
in one place keep track of shared memory
channels in one place and keep track of
external network connections another
place and provide a simpler API the
applications to to access all these
things is your Fossum paper available
anywhere it is there's a there's a this
it's on my web page it's called the wild
west of unix i/o okay well put that in
the show notes as well she raised the
issue of security could you say more
about the security comparison of unic
earn 'l - among
with it colonel so whenever the first XO
Colonels were built in the late 90s they
were all built using si and one of the
the big benefits was performance but
people didn't really care so much about
security because obviously you know they
just wanted to prove that they could
just build extremely high throughput or
very reliable systems and when we came
to buildings in the cloud
our primary goal way ahead of
performance was to build an end-to-end
secure system that is that no component
in a mirage kernel should be memory
unsafe that is it should guarantee that
you will not lead to lots of low-level
bugs where at all possible so in a
modern Mirage system only the runtime
the language runtime of for a camel and
a tiny tiny boot layer is actually
written in C everything from the device
drivers up so from the shared memory
abstractions to the the network
protocols to talk to Xen to the actual
coordination protocols who talk to the
host to the tcp/ip stack it's all
written in a camel and this means that
any single packet coming in is bounce
checked for for checking that doesn't
violate basic security properties all
the way through the kernel and you might
think that this is slightly paranoid but
if you follow the news then open SSL had
yet another serious exploit yesterday
called Hart lead and the way that
heartbleed works is that a simple
heartbeat through SSL to a virtual
machine sorry to a service was not buns
checked and this lets anyone on the
internet read up to 64 kilobytes of your
memory so this would just be impossible
in Mirage because the oh camel code that
underlies the the actual network stack
checks that every single access is
permitted with respect to the the
protocol specification that the program
has written so even if you make a
mistake and you try to step out of
bounds it will just raise an exception
and it will terminate the connection so
this is the kind of property that we're
trying to build all the way through our
our stacks and one of the really nice
things where a camel is that in addition
to giving you these low-level guarantees
for just checking memory safety it also
has one of the world's most
powerful module systems when it comes to
Peruvian languages and this means that
we can take lots of small well specified
simple modules and compose them to form
a much more complicated system without
violating a lot of the safety guarantees
that each of these modules have so a
module a modular solid programming is
very similar to object-oriented
programming except that it doesn't mix
up the concerns of state and and and
they and the actual data transformations
that are happening at the same time
through the code so it is purely trying
to say that we will specify well-defined
transformations over your code and not
worry so much about encapsulating the
actual data that's handled elsewhere so
the two major security gains from
mirages are modular programming through
high-level or camel code and low-level
garbage collection and bugs checking
throughout the entire system to make
sure that nothing escapes the the
garbage collector so that everything is
cleaned up where possible and Boncuk
were possible as well you've given us
some of the reasons why Oh camel is well
suited to building this type of system
would you tell us the story of how you
chose the language for this project and
anything else about oh camel that you
think people would be interested in sure
so as with all good things they started
with a cup of coffee in 2003 over over
an argument about an OpenSSH bug so back
when I was in the open as a developer
there was a very serious bug in OpenSSH
that was about a serious as the OpenSSL
bug from from last week and it resulted
it was a it was an integer overflow that
resulted in hundreds of millions of
hosts just getting hacked through
through worms and so I was sitting with
Dave Scott who's now at Citrix and we
were wondering why we couldn't just
build an equivalent in an in a safe
language and the reasons for this for
were many you know the idea that you
could build a fast server in a garbage
collector language was still not quite
believed by people back then and also
just the sheer amount of effort it would
take to re-implement these protocols
because there's so much of them and so
of course after had the coffee we just
said to give it a shot and my PhD turned
into solving a lot of the problems that
went into building one of these services
so I built lots of domain-specific
languages for packet parsing safely with
a no camel yet so maintaining
performance and lots of hooks to form
verify aspects of the system using model
checkers that would check the state
space so by about 2006 I finished my PhD
and we had an SSH server and DNS server
all built using a camel but there were
research prototypes and you published
those papers and we thought that they
that was the end of this story in 2006
both with joins M source which is
commercializing Xen and we used a camel
to build the control stack for one of
the earlier versions of the commercial
version of Zen which is now used by some
huge companies for example Rackspace
deploys their entire rack space cloud by
using some of the code we wrote and all
of this code was written in a no camel
so this is a database all of the
management stack and we published some
retrospectives and how a camel was a
really good good use for this it turns
out that back in those days there was
actually no other choice for building
these kind of embedded systems in a safe
language so go didn't exist then Russ
didn't exist then or camel was a 10 year
old operating system in in 2005 and it
had a reputation for being an absolutely
rock-solid runtime there's very few bugs
in there and a very simple runtime so
it's one that if we did find a bug we
could debug it ourselves without having
to to wade through millions of lines of
code and the faith no camel has just
been been born out through the last the
last 10 or 15 years because in the whole
time we use it commercially we found I
think one bug in the compiler that had
already been fixed in the next version
so it's just an extremely solid and well
engineered system that you can depend on
to build mission-critical code and then
the only problem became could we hire
people fast enough to to suit the needs
of a growing startup and it turns out
that was just no problem functional
programming is just becoming more and
more popular and people joined us
specifically so they could learn a camel
and actually improve their skills at the
same time as working on something as
exciting as em and the cloud so
generally is a win-win situation
and so the Mirage project grew out of
all of this this this work you mentioned
earlier how you compile a kernel using
the O camel compiler which inserts a lot
of other layers of software to build the
complete kernel walk us through the tool
chain if I want to build a
Mirage that does DNS or a web server
what are all the tools how do they work
together what's the result got it so
this is actually very very simple now my
colleague Amir chatter he published a
blog post and how you can go from a
Jekyll website which is a blog generator
to eunuch Colonel in 50 lines of code so
that's actually linked from the open
barrage website and the reason this is
so simple is because all of the code you
need to build a Mirage system is handled
by a package manager that Tomac has
Annie wrote called Oh Pam and so when
you install open it it downloads a
package database you'll be familiar with
these package systems for other
languages and it has all of the
infrastructure required to build to
build any Mirage library and then we
have a command line tool called Mirage
and you you give it two things you give
it a unique kernel source code for
example for a website and you give it a
little specification of how to compile
that source code and now there are
multiple ways you can compile the Mirage
application I could compile a web server
to run on my on my Mac OS machine so I
can debug it locally or I can compile it
to run in Mac OS or Linux but using the
full networking stack from Mirage so
instead of depending on the Linux kernel
it would just use our camel networking
stack instead and then finally I can get
rid of Mac OS entirely and recompile the
same source code into a Zen microkernel
all from the same same tree in the same
build system and so the Mirage
command-line tool gives you all the
options to pull this off so the workflow
is that you build your system using Mac
OS or whatever operating system you want
locally when you've debug didn't you're
happy with it you didn't simply
recompile everything and the output is a
Zen microkernel now to glue all of this
together we've actually been using other
people's services and so we use
something called Travis which is a
continuous integration system that runs
against github and so all we have to do
to build one of these kernels in
practice is that we push a source code
if to the Mirage website on github
Travis picks it up it builds a complete
copy of the website and it pushes the
resulting Zen microkernel into another
github repository so if you go to the
Mirage Organization github you
Mirage - www then you can go to Mirage -
WWWE point and that has the resulting
builds from from the Travis website so
everything we do is just tracked in
github so to build one of these websites
you just have to set up three
repositories set up Travis which is free
free for use and then use a cloud
service like Amazon or Rackspace to
actually run the resulting kernel and
everything can be done using existing
cloud services now the beautiful thing
is that whenever you commit these things
into github you know everything that
went into your deployed service so there
is nothing that we have that we cannot
track through get that we deploy in the
cloud so if I come back to this in ten
years I will have a version controlled
copy of everything I did to compile it
and this is a serious problem if you're
using existing cloud services where you
just lose track of what's going on very
very quickly and the final piece of
puzzle is we've just had support from a
company called Cody Oh if you go to CEO
di o comm that provided web-based ID and
they actually give us a container where
you can install Oh Pam purely from a
web-based interface and do all of the
editors source code without having to
have it installed locally so we have a
pure web based workflow we can log into
Co do build mirage using kernels and
deploy the results using Amazon ec2 and
I use Travis to continue the deployment
bills so it's all it's all nicely
integrated and working these days it's
still more complicated and using Heroku
but it's a great learning experience for
anyone who wants to you know work
through all of the layers that goes into
building one of these platforms of
service engines once you've got that
process in place how long is it from
when you hit save in your browser based
IDE before your Mirage kernel is booted
up and running so if you do a Travis if
you do a push to github and then get
Travis to build it it typically takes
about six or seven minutes for to build
the entire operating system and remember
this is doing it from scratch so it's
it's building up everything from open or
camel all the way through to your your
final Zen website by building a source
code based
push if you decide to build a binary
snapshots you could be doing the final
link in a matter of seconds so we have
some prototypes
if you do a minor change to a
configuration file you can have the
result deployed within five seconds - to
a cloud service and our latest work is
to try to bring this down to
milliseconds so the idea is that if you
want to do something that fixes a
critical security hole we should be able
to push the security fixed to github and
have all of our unique URLs updated
within seconds so none of this business
of us having to manually recompile and
track all of our layers of software
because we're tracking everything in get
we should just use git to itself trigger
rebuilds of all of our critical
infrastructure if I have web
applications written in one of the more
popular languages can you build a Mirage
microkernel with let's say a Ruby
runtime or a JVM
and then load your existing application
into that so this is this is as you
might imagine one of the most popular
questions that I get so it does take one
thing to build these unique kernel
systems it takes a bloody-minded
determination to not relax some of the
some of the stands that we take when
building the system the first place so
one of the decisions we made was we
wanted to have an understandable and
simple to use runtime and compiler
infrastructure and this is why we've
stuck with the camel all the way through
partly because it camel is a great
language to work in but also because
working in two languages it just gets so
much more complicated you have to deal
with linkage across the systems
differences in semantics and protecting
one from the other and before you know
it you just got a full operating system
so the the way to do multiple languages
is by building a unique kernel for Ruby
or a unique kernel for Python or unique
kernel for PHP and has actually been
quite a lot of progress in this space so
if you look at the modern set of
languages one of the most mature ones is
Hal VM by Galois systems and this is a
Haskell equivalent of garage but but
built using the Haskell style of
programming which is purely functional
and lazy
there's also a service unfortunate the
source code is no available yet but they
might have might have plans to release
it is Erlang and Zen which is also
another functional language based on
message passing and another one for Java
is called osv which has just been done
by the
the founders of the KVM hypervisor and
they have a focus on building much more
compatible systems using the using the
Java and go runtimes as well now one
thing that mirage has that these systems
don't have is this emphasis and modular
programming so we're we're and we're
focused less on backwards compatibility
and more on how to build this new
generation of really modular and
easy-to-use components that we can use
for for in multiple contexts but we
don't really have a focus in trying to
wrap existing systems such as Ruby on
Rails a website in Inter Mirage the
answer here is rewrite and restructure
it and the process of rerunning it will
actually improve the system
significantly because you typically come
up with new insights about how you want
to structure the system if you do want
to maintain the compatibility just from
a virtual machine running Linux and you
can you can you can control that entire
virtual machine using Mirage and and you
know switch it on and off and configure
the network stack but you could just use
virtualization to run code in the old
style and save all of the new stuff for
Mirage another talk you gave that I
watched you really emphasize how the
type system of a camel contributed to
your design goals in Mirage tell us
about that
right so when when when building a new
operating system it's impossible to
re-emphasize how easy it is to get
tangled up in all kinds of components
that are just interlocked and seemingly
lacking any form of structure one of the
reasons why o camel is such a wonderful
language to work with for this kind of
large-scale system is that it has really
two different modes of running whenever
you write a single or camel module it
has something called automatic type
inference and this means that whenever a
write a function I do not need to
declare that any given variable is an
integer or a string or some other kind
of data structure the use of that will
inform the the compiler about how it
what its type should be and if at any
point when writing my code or using
someone else's code two variables
disagree on the definition of one of the
variables this is a type error for
example if I try to add one to a string
then one of those is clearly a bug and
therefore the compiler will complain and
point out the the dissonance so local
hyper emphasis is extremely useful for
writing six into small bits of code and
we use this extensively just everywhere
through Mirage when it comes to
rewriting your device drivers and all
level systems we find that the O camel
code is just smaller and easier to read
then the equivalent written in C which
is the obviously the gold standard for
running this kind of systems code the
second half though is where our mode
really comes into its own which is a
module system so the module system has
no type inference it's a very explicit
way of wrapping some functionality and
enforcing abstraction barriers so let's
say for example I've got a file
descriptor and the file descriptor
Music's is an integer
you know camel I can actually say that I
want users in my file descriptor library
to only treat an FD as an abstract type
that is they will have no idea that it's
actually in an integer under the hood
but whenever this is compiled the
compiler checks that known is assuming
that an FD is an integer and then it
eliminates all of the the type
assertions at compile time so the this
abstraction that we put together using a
module system has no runtime cost it is
simply something that the compiler
checks and then it discards it it erases
it and the runtime looks very much like
C it's just an integer under the hood
that is that is being used in a very
normal context so this emphasis on
abstraction without cost is a really
really incredible feature of of building
big static type systems and the best way
to summarize this is something that Ron
Minsky from James Street came up with
which is that the O camel type system
makes illegal states unrepresentable
so that is if there is something that I
know is a programmer should never happen
we can probably use your camel type
system to enforce that abstraction and
we don't have to worry about that the
compiler worries about it for us for the
for the rest of the duration of the
lifetime of the library and given that
we have over a hundred hundred libraries
in our repositories we have about 2,000
third-party libraries written in our
camel it's obvious that we need to
depend on something other than human
beings to enforce a lot of these safety
properties and that's where the camel
type system is is just a wonderful thing
to use do you see a scenario where
running
a mirage inside a web browser creates
opportunity to do things easily that are
difficult or impossible to do right now
yes absolutely so this is our biggest
focus right now one of the one of the
reasons I came back to academia after
his interests in 2009 was because I was
very very concerned about the state of
personal data management and even in
2009 it was obvious that a lot of the
infrastructure that we are building for
a society is going into centralized
cloud systems so things like Dropbox and
Facebook and Google while incredibly
useful are centralized and somewhat of
an antithesis to the way that we
envision the internet developing in the
in the early optimistic nation we say so
the new system in Mirage we're building
is a replacement for your personal
homepage in your personal infrastructure
where your entire stack of everything
from DNS to HTTP to storage to
communication is handled by embedded
devices running on armed nodes that are
built using Mirage and the idea behind
the system is that if you built one of
these system using using conventional
technology you would find that you would
be left having to manage an entire
network of machines and devices yourself
and this would quickly become a security
nightmare so what we want is us to write
high-level code in a camel and to
compile it and track it using this gate
workflow that I described earlier and
result and run the result in embedded
devices that are all at the edge of the
network for example in your house at
your work place within your mobile phone
and even embedded within web browsers
and one of the key advantages of a camel
is that we can compile the same source
code into all of these very foreign
environments so the Zen hypervisor
itself has just had support for our arm
so it's not possible to run Zen not only
on x86 but also on a bunch of new arm
boards for example the cubieboard to the
QB truck and the new Chromebooks can all
run Zen because the the ARM architecture
now supports virtualization and we also
have a version barrage that is being
developed at the moment that compiles to
a Raspberry Pi kernel as well so if you
have a Raspberry Pi you can just write
some humble source code and just boot it
up from scratch on an existing little
Raspberry Pi device
so we're really optimistic that that a
lot of the code we've developed for the
cloud-based system will actually help us
build what we call the edge cloud that
is a network of devices that are as easy
to use as a cloud but all
self-organizing self-managing self
encrypting so that they will not leak
their contents to other people and
provide people with the ability to run
their own little clouds that can
communicate and federate in a very
natural way so this system is called my
mode where it's Nymo te tor org it's all
going to be open source of course and
we're going to be launching it at OS
kona in july so this is this is
something we're furiously hacking on at
the moment as the extension to our home
pages and so on that we we described
earlier so it's very very exciting to be
taking Mirage into all of these new new
embedded devices trying to figure out
how to run it and lots of foreign
environments you've written a book about
oh camel real-world Oh camel functional
programming for the masses it sounds
like the ambition of your book is
broader than teaching people how to
build an operating system kernel
McCampbell is in a weird position in
about 2009 back when we first started
discussing the book it had a very small
community of users but those users were
using a camel in extremely
mission-critical situations for example
we were using in Zen for some very
serious management stacks that if they
went down into our data centers would go
down there's a comedy called Jane Street
which is a trading firm in New York that
pumps billions of dollars through a
camel every day and all of their trades
were ignorant camel and there are
similar uses in aerospace and so on but
it was a community of about 10 to 15 can
have very very large users and it didn't
really have a tail of hobbyists and
people just playing around with the
language and part of this is because it
was just very very badly documented and
it lacked a package manager that unified
the community there's a number of
efforts but for whatever reasons they
never quite gelled so I was sitting in a
bar in Tokyo after one of the function
programming conference with Ron Minsky
and we decided in the heat of the moment
to write a quick book about about oh
camel and her friend Brian O'Sullivan
told us about O'Reilly and he told us
about his book real-world Haskell which
for Haskell was just a
formative book and just propelling to a
wider audience just how simple Haskell
could be for a number of situations but
of course writing a book is just always
ten times more effort than you realize
because in the process of writing the
book there's a bunch of stuff that
you've internalized for whatever reason
in the past that you just cannot explain
to somebody else for example how the
standard library works or why you have
to do this little workaround for this
particular bit of infrastructure and we
spend about a couple of years fixing a
lot of problems in a camel that made it
difficult for newcomers to to give it a
try so the story of real-world a camel
is that it ended up with me starting a
research group in Cambridge called the
camel labs that took on a lot of the
responsibility from the core maintenance
of a camel for building an ecosystem
around the language so mirage is one
example where we're writing a lot of a
camel code but my group of camel labs
also worries about things like package
management making sure that our camels
type system is stable and that we do a
lot of testing of the system just all of
the bits and pieces you need to do to
make sure that the compiler remains a
stable and very very robust component
for the negative the next couple of
decades of use just as it has in the
past so real look real world a camel
also took a few decisions it's a very
opinionated book so one of the problems
of camels had in the past is that the
standard library is very very minimal
because it's just designed for use for
the compiler and not by the wider
community so Jane Street which is a
trading firm in New York open sourced
their entire standard library which
they've written millions of lines of
their company code using and this
centered library is called core and it
cleans up a number of aspects of a
standard library and provides hundreds
of data structures that are often best
to breed in any language for example the
hash table implementation in core is
ridiculously fast even when compared to
one of the more optimized Java ones for
example and so real will a camel decided
that we would use core is the exclusive
way to introduce newcomers to the
language and not really talk about a lot
of the old code if you wanted to learn
about how to program using the normal
standard library there were other
resources online to learn that so our
decision was we wanted to tell people
how we use a camel
or are used in industry and not so much
worry about some of the more academic
uses of of functional programming that
have normally been used to teach to
teach people about languages like oh
camel we have a ban on compilers for
example so nowhere in world a camel will
you find any tutorials on how to build a
compiler there's many many books and
using a camel for that we instead talk
about building web services how to view
JSON parsing for example and talk about
building lots of little small
applications that you might find a use
for in the normal workplace Oh camel is
not one of the more popular languages
among web developers tell us about the
history of the language right it's it's
not a popular language for web
developers because of its of its roots
in academia so or camel started off as
an extension to a very rich history of
programming formal formal systems so in
the in the 60s for example Robin Robin
Milner was at Stanford and researching
lots of fundamental approaches to
describing various computer science
concepts and this resulted after a
number of decades at work by some very
smart people a system called standard ml
and standard ml is still used and
developed these days and it's often used
as teaching materials for courses in the
East Coast but Senator Mel was perhaps
they made a mistake of adopting a formal
specification so this meant that if you
wanted to change and evolve standard ml
you had to argue with the Standards
Committee to make sure that your changes
could be reflected eventually in the in
the definition of the language so
meanwhile in France
Zev Villa wah and a bunch of other
professors from inria were started
developing a camel light which was an
alternative to standard ml and in about
1996 they released a camel which was the
the camel compiler with a native code
backend that would generate extremely
fast x86 and arm and PowerPC and SPARC
code and also an interesting object
system on top of it that would let you
actually build conventional
object-oriented code on top of the
normal ml style programming system so a
camel in his current form has been
around since about 1996 but it's
commercially been you
to build academic systems for example
one of the biggest theorem provers
that's used by hundreds of academics
across the world called is written
in oh camel and on top of the Aesir
improvers some very large system such as
the concert which is a certified C
compiler that guarantees that it will
compile code correctly is built on build
on top of that as well so oh camel has
traditionally been used to build
compilers for example the original
version of rust was written using a
camel and it hasn't really developed a
web ecosystem of people developing these
styles of libraries but if you go to
this other world of building parlors
it's it's an extremely popular in
pragmatic language so one of the things
we've spent the last 10 years doing is
developing libraries and infrastructure
for building these kind of network based
subsystems as well so a lot of the core
library from James Street is around how
to build TCP services and so on and a
lot of the libraries in Mirage these
days are all about lightweight libraries
for web programming now one of the most
exciting things to happen to Campbell in
the last few years is something called
JSF a camel and this is a compiler for
normal camel bytecode that outputs the
result in two extremely efficient
JavaScript so it turns out that unlike a
lot of other languages the the execution
of a camel maps on the JavaScript very
very well you can consider a camel to be
a typed version of JavaScript and so
most recently Facebook has developed a
new language call hack and this language
which is a significant provision of PHP
is actually run in a web browser the
language compiler is written using a
camel it's compiled into a web browser
using javascript and Facebook have an ID
where any developer writing hack code
will actually in the browser type check
the code and give the feedback
instantaneously all without having to go
to a normal normal tool chain so this is
a great example of just building an
entirely new language in a camel
compiling it to JavaScript building the
ID framework so that you have a nice
kind of you know online editor workflow
and not having to deal with any kind of
native compilation at all so camel is
incredibly portable when it comes to
building these kind of embedded services
and meanwhile other people have built I
backends for our android back-end for
mobile devices different
microcontrollers we've of course run it
as an operating system and also as
kernel modules and generally we haven't
really found anywhere where we can't
take a little bit of a camel code and
make it map onto efficiently on to some
other back-end so it is really a Swiss
Army knife for these very foreign
environments that we increasingly to run
coding if listeners would like to learn
more about Mirage other than the
resources you've already mentioned which
will all be in the show notes is there
anything else you'd like them to look at
so one thing we're doing at the moment
is because Mirage has been included into
the google Summer of Code and the open
source project for women initiatives run
by the gnome project is that where we're
working on improving the documentation
and generally trying to polish up all of
the resources available so everything
that we do we try to put in the website
on Open Mirage org and the opener or
wiki and documentation is itself in
Mirage application so one thing we
really encourage people to do is that if
you give mirage a try and you discover
there's some problem in the in the
documentation or some something that
needs clarification it's a sensible
request that is to build the Mirage
website yourself and to edit the the
markdown files inside the repository and
and to actually send us a pull request
and kind of experience the end-to-end
workflow and once you do this a number
of people have done this have commented
me that they then gone off and try to
run their own home pages using Mirage as
well so it's it's a nice way to kind of
get into workflow and just be be part of
the community as well apart from the de
Mirage website one of the harder things
when using Mirage is to learn how to run
these kernels in the cloud so because
unfortunately there's no real standard
for a lot of these cloud api's so once
you have this end kernel you need to use
either OpenStack or cloud stack or
Amazon or one of the other bespoke API
for example the on app API and it can be
very very confusing trying to figure
these things out and that's something
our small development team doesn't
really have the resources to to you know
figure out by ourselves so if you do end
up running mirage kernels just you know
write a blog post about it send us an
email critic get having issues they're
all on github.com slash mirage Mirage
and we're really happy to hear about
people
using it for interesting things one of
the most motivational things but doing
open sources just hearing what people
are up to you're right so and quite
often people just don't realize that we
like hearing that so just feel free to
drop the email list and email anytime
and just explain what you're up to
listeners would like to learn more about
your work what websites would you point
them to so we we we have an aggregator
running on open market org and we also
have an increasing amount of blogging
activity on an emote org which is where
the personal data uses a mirage
we'll all be hosted we also the core
team also maintains blogs as well so
whenever we do something of interest we
tend to just write a quick blog post
about it so my home page is annealed a
wrinkled or org and you can also find on
the Mirage home page atomic resume i've
richard Marty and David Scott who are
the other core maintainer is mirage and
they all maintain their own blogs and of
course we federate the the results
through at him and just aggregate that
on to Auntie Mirage yeah there's some
really exciting work going on as well
and this is somewhere where we could
relieve some help is to build a clean
slate SSL stack at the moment so we we
had two extremely motivated and smart
people who've decided to work in this
Hanna's and David and they've actually
built from scratch a clean slate SSL
stack that obviates a lot of the known
attacks against against SSL but of
course the thing missing is a lot of
people reading it and criticizing the
code and doing code review so so they're
also planning to do a blog post series
about the adventures they've had in
building a clean site SSL stack and
people who want to follow that she just
keep an eye on the Mirage homepage and
will update that across the course of
the summer
so in general we just need people
reading these blog posts and and also
just giving us critical feedback as well
about about the usability this this
whole this whole system
well definitely get that in the show
notes that gives us to the end of the
interview anneal thank you very much for
speaking to software engineering radio
it's been a pleasure I look forward to
to seeing how this project develops
based on your readers feedback we are
looking for feedback we would love for
our listeners to go on I too
and write a review of the show let us
know how we're doing and this is Robert
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening thanks for listening to SD
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at se - radio net to support us
you can advertise su Radio by clicking
the day credit delicious or slide
buttons on the site or by talking about
this on Facebook Twitter or your own
blog if you have feedback specific to an
episode please use the commenting
feature on the site so that other
listeners can respond to your comments
as well this and all of the episodes of
se radio is licensed under the creative
commons two-point-five license please
see the website for details thanks again
for your support
[Music]
[Applause]